<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Saheed's Second Brain</title>
        <link>https://saheed.codes/</link>
        <description>Ahmed Saheed's Encyclopedia | Second Brain</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 13:16:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>Feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>© Ahmed Saheed 2022</copyright>
        <category>Second Brain</category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Log]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/log</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/log</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[What is going on ? ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>August 2022</h3>
<p><img src="https://100r.co/media/content/travel/penelakut_01.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p>My words are limited, perphaps enormous on the inside but as I try to force these words onto my leaflet, they seem to flutter away and vanish, refusing to be expressed in any precise form.</p>
<p>Lately, i've been living in a state emotional numbness which opposes my real self who's filled with empathy and bursting in emotions. perhaps, this is because nothing really special has been taking place on my daily life or as a result of lack of friends with like mindset or even lack of inner drive.</p>
<p>Although, somethimes i tend to to convience myself that this might actually be the right lifestyle for myself. Away from the madding crowd, away in an <strong>inferior</strong> state of repose and away in silence during an age of noise.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Certainly, the word <code>exile</code> itself now enters the ears more harshly through a sort of conviction and popular belief, and strikes the listener to be detestible. For that is people's verdicts, but wise men on the whole reject the people's decree</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I am aware that in my spirit lives a sort of inborn restlessness. For my mind is certainly very unsettled, darting about and directing thoughts to all places known and unknown. Perhaps I am a wanderer who's struggling to endure solemnity.</p>
<p>I've been working on <code>leaflet</code>, which i'm current using to document this log. This is the first tool i've created for the sole purpose of my need i.e documenting my feelings and jornaling. This project has brought some tranquil into my wandering mind. It's strongly inspired by <a href="https://100r.co/site/left.html">100r.co's Leaf</a></p>
<p>I'm currently reading On The Shortness Of Life By Seneca.</p>
<p>&lt;!-- ---</p>
<h3>September 2022</h3>
<p>Today, 9/9/22 i got my final intern interview at microsoft scheduled. I have no idea how i feel. I'm very positive though. --&gt;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Leaflet]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/leaflet</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/leaflet</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Minimal distractionless markdown editor!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;</p>
<p>&lt;video src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/87912847/188292656-94da4c10-7fb3-464f-8fad-270b255afaee.mov&quot; controls=&quot;controls&quot;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;</p>
<p>&lt;/p&gt;</p>
<p>Leaflet, a <strong>minimal distractionless markdown editor</strong> designed to quickly navigate between multiple <code>.md</code> files in a directory and its sub directories. It features a clean mathematical typesetting, chemical equation rendering, code blocks highlighting, writing statistics and a speed-reader.</p>
<p>I created this &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Leaflet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; class=&quot;external &quot;&gt;application&lt;/a&gt; to help me cope with note taking during school lectures as most of my lecturers spoke too fast. This application is made available as a free and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Leaflet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; class=&quot;external &quot;&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt; software.</p>
<p>&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Leaflet/releases/download/v0.0.1/Leaflet-0.0.1.dmg&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://api.iconify.design/simple-icons:apple.svg?color=%23888888&quot;/&gt;
OS X Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Leaflet/releases/download/v0.0.1/Leaflet-Setup-0.0.1.exe&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://api.iconify.design/icomoon-free:windows.svg?color=%23888888&quot;/&gt;
Windows Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Leaflet/releases/download/v0.0.1/leaflet_0.0.1_amd64.snap&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://api.iconify.design/codicon:terminal-ubuntu.svg?color=%23888888&quot;/&gt;
Linux Downloads&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</p>
<p>&lt;/div&gt;</p>
<hr>
<h1>Features</h1>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>🖋 Editing</strong>: Switch between editing and preview mode seemlessly</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>⚛️ Maths &amp; Chemical Equation Typesetting</strong>: Leaflet renders mathematical, physics and chemical equation out of the box.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Pandoc Support</strong>: Easily export your <code>.md</code> files to <code>.pdf</code> and <code>.docx</code> files</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>📄 Uses Files</strong>: Leaflet works with users file system directly instead of an external database.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>🌙 Dark / Light Mode</strong>: Supports your system specified theme.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>✨ Simplicity</strong>: Leaflet focuses on simplicity and provides only necessary features needed.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Word Suggestion</strong>: Provides about 5,000 english word and synonyms suggestion</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>🕉 Bidirectional Text</strong>: Automatically detect BIDI - text and displays logiaclly.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2>Installation</h2>
<p>You'd have to install <a href="https://github.com/jgm/pandoc/blob/master/INSTALL.md">pandoc</a> to export <code>.md</code> to other formats.</p>
<p>You can also run Leaflet locally from the command line:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ git clone https://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Leaflet.git &amp;&amp; cd Leaflet
$ yarn install
$ yarn dev
</code></pre>
<p>Or Build</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ git clone https://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Leaflet.git &amp;&amp; cd Leaflet
$ yarn install
$ yarn build
</code></pre>
<hr>
<h1>More Features</h1>
<ul>
<li>Support media like <code>mp3</code>, <code>iframe</code> and <code>video</code></li>
<li>Displays a table of content on demand</li>
<li>Renders task list, tables and footnotes  quite nicely</li>
<li>File statistics displayed in the footer (speed-reader, word count, date).</li>
</ul>
<h2>Extras</h2>
<ul>
<li>Leaflet is strongly inspired by <a href="https://github.com/hundredrabbits/left">Left</a> and <a href="https://github.com/pacocoursey/Opus">Opus</a>.</li>
<li>Leaflet source code  licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">BY-NC-SA 4.0</a>.</li>
<li>Pull Requests are welcome!</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Javari]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/javari</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/javari</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A modern day version of Christ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>God is real and he using me for a bigger purpose<br>
So fuck the world that would have you think that a nigga is  worthless</p>
<p>Sometimes I think that these verses can help a person<br>
way more than the ones they reading in churches on days of worship .</p>
<p>No disrespect to the Lord and Savior, that ain't just ego. I just observe that them words no longer relate to people because  modern times are flooded with dollar signs.
And social media stunting, most niggas just wanna shine.</p>
<p>They frame of mind so far removed from the days and times of Nazareth. Life these days is a labyrinth, in a maze so elaborate we barely get through half of it before it's too late.</p>
<p>All of that to say maybe the hood need a new faith<br>
A new story about a boy from not too far where you stay</p>
<hr>
<p>His momma was a virgin named Yolanda<br>
And she raised him on her own, after she was disowned.
Her momma called her a liar, said &quot;Get the fuck out my home&quot;<br>
Since you wanna be grown<br>
So, there she was now, seventeen and alone.</p>
<p>But this lil' boy that grew in her stomach made her feel strong<br>
The angels paid her a visit one night and let it be known<br>
This was God's child, woman behold this miracle.<br>
She shed tears because she never believed in the spiritual<br>
But her heart was pure and she was good<br>
For eighteen years she raised him on Section 8 in the cold embrace of the hood.
Did the best as she could, the boy was named Javari<br>
Walked with the spirit of his father emanating from body.</p>
<hr>
<p>Back in the hood, look at lil' Vari preach<br>
His words were full of spirit, his truth it would always reach<br>
He laid his hands on Toya, when niggas called her a freak<br>
And told her that God loved her no matter who she let beat</p>
<p>But being promiscuous is a sign that there's something deep<br>
That troubles her soul, the day she lets it go, she'll find peace<br>
She broke down admitting her stepfather had touched her for years<br>
She kept it secret for fear of her mother's grief<br>
Now the bitterness she feels for that nigga is at a peak<br>
And her lack of self-esteem is the reason that she would sleep with anybody and not think twice,</p>
<p>Javari spoke calmly<br>
Instructing her to forgive her stepfather<br>
Though he was wrong he was sick<br>
Afflicted by evil, but the power to switch<br>
How you feel about people who hurt you is truly a gift<br>
The thing that can make you rich or keep you down in a ditch<br>
If you refuse to let go of the ground, then how can you lift?<br>
Into the sky where you belong with the most high<br>
Now wipe those tears from your eyes, my father wants you to fly.</p>
<hr>
<p>Back in the hood, Javari built up a following<br>
Niggas put down they pistols eventually<br>
And stopped swallowing molly pills Instead their bodies filled with spirit<br>
Twelve lil' homies soaking up every word that they hearing</p>
<p>The neighborhood changed in attitude and appearance<br>
Police dumbfounded by lack of crime and they swear it's a fluke<br>
Not knowing the truth, that this a miracle<br>
Niggas is waking up with the powers that be they fearing</p>
<hr>
<p>So government keep a tap on Javari and those who practice adherence<br>
To things he teaching and then comes to interference</p>
<p>They stormed the hood, guns out<br>
Bust into the house that he slept in<br>
A warrant claiming suspicion of drug possession<br>
But Vari sat calmly as if he had been expecting<br>
Heart full of love, even for those who need to oppress him</p>
<p>They told him &quot;Hands up&quot; and he did just as they directed<br>
They fired on him, claiming they thought he reached for a weapon<br>
He laid on the floor breathless, blood leaking from his chest</p>
<p>Plus a bullet-hole through both of his palms, ain't that a message?</p>
<hr>
<p>The neighborhood was stressing
The son of God murdered and carried away on stretcher by the oppressor.</p>
<p>Three days later, the coroner pulled the table<br>
And what happened next is like something you see on cable or hear in a fable</p>
<p>He was suddenly able to open his eyes, look at him rise, the coroner was surprised<br>
Without a word Javari walked out, went straight to the hood<br>
The people couldn't believe it, they froze right where they stood</p>
<p>As he walked by, God flowing from every inch of his frame<br>
He said</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Hear me out my niggas, let me be your proof, my father is real and through love, homie, peace can be found. I died for you, so that one day you would be able to see you a child of God, just like me&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Letter to my future self]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/letter-to-myself</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/letter-to-myself</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A ponder on my past, present and future]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Hi Saheed,</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Wait! perhaps you intend to read the <a href="/second-brain/log">log</a> book instead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This letter goes from my current self to my future self. I am currently writing from a dining table after having a hot bowl of noodles while listening to a chakra meditation sound. You might someday be reading this at a different place, in a different time doing absoluetly something else.</p>
<p>I haven't written such a letter like this throughout my existence, but i'd try to make it organic as possible.</p>
<p><img src="/relief.jpeg" alt=""></p>
<p>To begin,  i'd need to rewind a bit to your last days of secondary school. I think this letter would be absolutely incomplete without that flashback.</p>
<h3>Early 2019</h3>
<p>At that point your life felt abysmal and lacked meaning, You had just gotten into SS3 the final point of the Nigerian Secondary Education system. This was one of the most memorable moments of your life. You were quite young then  perphaps 15 or 16yo, getting ready for college and  embedding into your brain your then assumed imagination of a college student. At that age you hadn't understood anything about your thought process, You only did whatever you felt would please your peers irrespective of your parent words which were considered a burden. You lived in a very delusional and detestable bubble called life. Things really went fast! You eventually encircled yourself with a very wrong set of individuals which you looked up to and called your friends.</p>
<p>Time went by, and things got worst. You'd started using drugs, forgotten the nostalgic childhood dream of becoming an astronaut. Your imagination of being in a space suit, wandering the moon and being the like of  Dr. Ben Carson had suddenly been swallowed by this darkness within your inner self. What had really happended? Can you recall?</p>
<p>This irrational way of life lasted a while and your parent started questioning. They became quite worried, the darkeness was visible around your dads conjunctiva. What and where have i done wrong were questions he asked himself. He felt terribly sad and you knew it. But you were to busy apeasing your so called friends!</p>
<hr>
<h3>Late 2019</h3>
<p>You'd finally graduated and a magnanimous graduation party was thrown for you, It wasn't necessary, but it was done none the less at the expense of your parent. Your grades wasn't excellent neither was it up to expectations but your parents still accepted it.</p>
<p>Graduation had come to an end, all of your collegues and friends had moved on and splitted all around the country. You remained home waiting to be admitted into a university. Your parent ran helter-skelter to make sure you'd gotten accepted in your desired university, all to no avail.</p>
<p>But your ill habits remained and needed to be sustained. You took forcefully from your parent purse. You felt this wasn't anything wrong besides it's for your parent! This continued till they couldn't take it any longer and became enraged by your attitude, your appearance and your way of life as a whole. You lacked  sense of remourse and empathy due to your emotional numbness caused by this sickness.</p>
<p>Now you hadn't heard from any university yet and you felt stuck in a chasm between your current illusion and reality. You became self aware but couldn't help it.  Your parents where still willing to help. They lamented though but never left your side, they always wanted the best. You ended up in a mental facility.</p>
<p>You had settled in quite nicely in this new place, feeling serene and a stong sense of calm being far away from the hustle and bustle of the outer world. The inhabitants had shown you love, kindness and affection irrespective of some random arguements from time to time. Some were quite educated, others lay men but the majority was soldiers.</p>
<p>You'd been clean for a while now, spending time reading books like <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/347852.The_Road_Less_Traveled">the road less travelled</a> and <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/773020.Abnormal_Psychology">Abnormal Psychology</a>, playing card game, table tennis and experimenting with psycho therapy.</p>
<p>You'd made friends with some really smart fellows like Dr Abdul-Salam, Dr Chineye , Uche the American college <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean%27s_list">dean enlisted</a> dropout who i was greatly influenced by and the Civil Engineering graduate from University of Lagos.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Early &amp; Mid 2020</h3>
<p>You had been allowed to leave this facility because you had to resume college at University of Lagos. Prior to resumption you'd been warned about relapse by both your therapist and your parents, your dad in particular. You'd also promised not to let them down.</p>
<p>Weeks went by as a freshman in college, you were doing great, not until you met some of your old peers from secondary school and decided to let yourself and loved once abashed and conscience-stricken.</p>
<p>This relapse was beyond your belief and far-fetched. It left you emotionally distorted. Those old darkness started creeping their way back into your life and this time eating deep into your endocardium. Your actions were outside your cognitive comprehension. It sucked and you knew it ! You felt like a swineherd returning to a pigsty immediately after taking hot shower.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Late 2020</h3>
<p>You'd become intolerable by your parent and your actions became notable and detesteble by the society around.</p>
<p>You decided to leave, perhaps it felt unbearable after what happend the afternoon you departed home. You weren't ready to feel any sort of remorse, instead you sought fault in your loved once and your upbringing. Delaying gratification and shying away from your reality. You were realistically disgusting and highly loathed!</p>
<p>You left, perphaps dad got back from work asking where you were or he was called that same moment of you departure, who knows. I wonder how he spent that night. Perphas so pained, he layed awake all night wiping the tears that rolled down his cheeks.</p>
<p>You'd decided to trade your comfort, satiety, education and most importantly your loved ones for an absolutely nonworthy cause. You accepted your own self made lies!</p>
<p>None the less he still came looking for you. He loved you down to earth! He saw something positively distinct and clearcut about you.</p>
<p>With a leap of fate, he believed in you and sent you 3,198 miles away from home for enquire quality education and pursue a better life. He begged not to be disappointed.</p>
<hr>
<h3>2021 Starting Anew</h3>
<p><img src="/tranquil.jpeg" alt=""></p>
<p>I ended up in Europe, unbelievable! i took awhile to to clearly grasp the message (<a href="/second-brain/cities-ambition">cities-ambition</a>) of this new society. I felt a bit overwhelmed at first about the protrayed solemnity of my new settlement, it felt absolutely contrary to what i was used to.</p>
<p>Time passed, I'd started a new school, settled in nicely and remained alone, not out of choice but out of fear for having wrong friends again and going down the old route i'd just miraculously escaped.</p>
<p>Lectures at school initially felt like a conundrum. I had decided to take Computer Science which deep down i'm very capable of handling. I felt very defeated by the workload but never let go. I struggled and couragously passed my first exam in europe.</p>
<h3>2022</h3>
<p>Away from the madding crowd, living a silent life in the age of noise, i've fellen in love with <a href="/books">books</a> and <a href="https://github.com/ahmedsaheed">programming</a> also mountaineering but haven't had a chance to climb on yet.</p>
<p>I've grown alot also learnt a reasonable amount of stuff.  I turned 19yo few months ago! I really wonder how time passes bye so fast. The transformation in my life over a couple of years has left me perplexed. I have acquired a more broaden and enlightened view of myself and the larger society.</p>
<p>Enough time has been spent pondering on my true self. i.e who i am now and who i want to really be. I have found the subtleness in self love and societal good. I have also outlined some noticable flaws to be worked on. Most of these are easier said than done, but deep down it's for nobody except oneself.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I currently see myself as a sailor and my body as a ship. This ship sails on an ocean consisting of all sort of things. My job as a sailor is to protect this ship from sinking at all cost. Making it sacred and safe from danger.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I would keep writing to you more often in absolute honesty.
I hope you're doing exceptionally well whenever you read this.</p>
<p>Yours truthfully,
Saheed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Quotes]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/quotes</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/quotes</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Some quote to live by]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Some quote to live by</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>I am persuaded that normal human beings are biologically built for an activity that is aimed towards a goal and that idleness, or aimless work gives rise to suffering and to entropy</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Primo Levi</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>We took risks, we knew we took them; things have come against us, and therefore we have no cause to complain, but bow to the will of providence, determined still to do our best to the last</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Robert Falcon Scott</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>The one great advantage which inexperience confers on an amateur is that he is not bogged down by the tradition or precedence. To him, all things appears simple and he chooses straightforward solutions to the problem he faces. Often, of cause, it defeats the sucess his seeking, and sometimes it has tragic results, but the man himself doesn't know this when he sets out on his adventure</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Walt Unsworth</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>But there are some men for whom the unattanable has a special attraction. Usually they are not experts: their ambition and fantasies are strong enough to brush aside the doubt which more cautious men might have. Determination and faith are their strongest weapons. At best such men are regarded as eccentric; at worst, mad ...</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Walt Unsworth</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>The more impropable the situation and the greater the demand on a man, the more sweetly his blood flows later in release from all the tension. The possiblity of danger serves merely to sharpen his awareness and control. And perphas this is rationale to all risky activities: You delibrately raise the ante of effort and concentration in order, as its were, to clear your mind of all trivialities.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>A. Alvarez</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>It is a fundamental law of nature that to evolve one has to push one’s limits, which is painful, in order to gain strength—whether it’s in the form of lifting weights, facing problems head-on, or in any other way. Nature gave us pain as a messaging device to tell us that we are approaching, or that we have exceeded, our limits in some way. At the same time, nature made the process of getting stronger require us to push our limits. Gaining strength is the adaptation process of the body and the mind to encountering one’s limits, which is painful. In other words, both pain and strength typically result from encountering one’s barriers. When we encounter pain, we are at an important juncture in our decision-making process</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Ray Dalio</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>What, if some day or night a demon were to steal after you into your loneliest loneliness and say to you: 'This life as you now live it and have lived it, you will have to live once more and innumerable times more; and there will be nothing new in it, but every pain and every joy and every thought and sigh and everything unutterably small or great in your life will have to return to you, all in the same succession and sequence—even this spider and this moonlight between the trees, and even this moment and I myself. The eternal hourglass of existence is turned upside down again and again, and you with it, speck of dust!'</p>
<p>Would you not throw yourself down and gnash your teeth and curse the demon who spoke thus? Or have you once experienced a tremendous moment when you would have answered him: 'You are a god and never have I heard anything more divine.' If this thought gained possession of you, it would change you as you are or perhaps crush you. The question in each and every thing, 'Do you desire this once more and innumerable times more?' would lie upon your actions as the greatest weight. Or how well disposed would you have to become to yourself and to life?</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Nietzsche</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Theming In React]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/react-theming</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/react-theming</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Theming isn't that tricky!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lately, the use of multiple themes on web and mobile applications has risen immersely. While developing this website, I struggled during implementation this feature.</p>
<p>I have decided to write this brief note on next js and react theming.</p>
<p>There are many ways to implement theming in react, but I have decided to explain two only.</p>
<h3>prerequisite</h3>
<p>I assert you already have a react environment to work with, if not you can easily create one using:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">npx create-next-app@latest
</code></pre>
<p>or</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">npx create-react-app my-app
</code></pre>
<h3>Implementing the theming.</h3>
<p>First Approaching - using the <a href="https://github.com/pacocoursey/next-themes">next theme libary</a></p>
<p>You'd need to add the libary to your project:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ npm install next-themes
# or
$ yarn add next-themes
</code></pre>
<p>In your <code>pages/_app.js</code> file, you'd need to add the following line:</p>
<pre><code class="language-js">import { ThemeProvider } from &quot;next-themes&quot;

function MyApp({ Component, pageProps }) {
    return (
        &lt;ThemeProvider&gt;
            &lt;Component {...pageProps} /&gt;
        &lt;/ThemeProvider&gt;
    )
}

export default MyApp
</code></pre>
<p>Then implement your style</p>
<pre><code class="language-css">:root {
    /* Your default theme */
    --background: white;
    --foreground: black;
}

[data-theme=&quot;dark&quot;] {
    --background: black;
    --foreground: white;
}
</code></pre>
<p>Lastly, create a theme button component in your <code>components/theme-button.js</code> file:</p>
<pre><code class="language-js">import { createContext, useEffect } from &quot;react&quot;
import { WiDaySunny } from &quot;react-icons/wi&quot;
import { MdOutlineDarkMode } from &quot;react-icons/md&quot;
import { useTheme } from &quot;next-themes&quot;

const mode = () =&gt; {
    const { theme, setTheme } = useTheme()
    const toggleDarkMode = () =&gt; {
        if (theme == &quot;light&quot;) {
            setTheme(&quot;dark&quot;)
        } else {
            setTheme(&quot;light&quot;)
        }
    }

    return (
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;button onClick={toggleDarkMode}&gt;
                {theme === &quot;light&quot; ? (
                    &lt;WiDaySunny style={{ color: &quot;black&quot; }} /&gt;
                ) : (
                    &lt;MdOutlineDarkMode style={{ color: &quot;white&quot; }} /&gt;
                )}
            &lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    )
}

export default mode
</code></pre>
<p>Second Approach - Implement the theming yourself.</p>
<p>Before we begin, we'd make use of react hook <a href="https://usehooks.com/useLocalStorage/"><code>useLocalStorage</code></a> which stores the users selected theme in local storage so that it persists through a page refresh.</p>
<p>We'd Also need our theme colors and element specified out in our stylesheet.</p>
<p>And with all these basic stuff out, we're good to go!</p>
<p>To begin, create a <code>hooks</code> folder in your root directory. Add a new javascript file in the directory like so <code>useLocalStorage.js</code>.</p>
<p>Now in your <code>useLocalStorage.js</code> file lets add some code to allow SSR[^1] and SSG[^2] work decently.</p>
<pre><code class="language-js">import { useState } from &quot;react&quot;

export function useLocalStorage(key, initialValue) {
    const [storedValue, setStoredValue] = useState(() =&gt; {
        if (typeof window === &quot;undefined&quot;) {
            return initialValue
        }
        try {
            // Get from local storage by key
            const item = window.localStorage.getItem(key)
            // Parse stored json or if none return initialValue
            return item ? JSON.parse(item) : initialValue
        } catch (error) {
            // If error also return initialValue
            console.log(error)
            return initialValue
        }
    })
    const setValue = (value) =&gt; {
        try {
            // Allow value to be a function so we have same API as useState
            const valueToStore = value instanceof Function ? value(storedValue) : value
            // Save state
            setStoredValue(valueToStore)
            // Save to local storage
            if (typeof window !== &quot;undefined&quot;) {
                window.localStorage.setItem(key, JSON.stringify(valueToStore))
            }
        } catch (error) {
            // A more advanced implementation would handle the error case
            console.log(error)
        }
    }
    return [storedValue, setValue]
}
</code></pre>
<p>On completion of the hook, we'll need to implement a function which makes our theming work.</p>
<p>Implementing this is fairly easy when done correctly.
To get started let's create a component called <code>theme.js</code> in our component's folder. In our <code>theme.js</code> file lets implement this function</p>
<pre><code class="language-js">import { createContext, useEffect } from &quot;react&quot;
import { useLocalStorage } from &quot;../hooks/useLocalStorage&quot;
import { WiDaySunny } from &quot;react-icons/wi&quot;
import { MdOutlineDarkMode } from &quot;react-icons/md&quot;

function mode() {
    const [theme, setTheme] = useLocalStorage(&quot;theme&quot;, &quot;light&quot;)

    useEffect(() =&gt; {
        if (
            localStorage.theme === &quot;dark&quot; ||
            (!(&quot;theme&quot; in localStorage) &amp;&amp;
                window.matchMedia(&quot;(prefers-color-scheme: dark)&quot;).matches)
        ) {
            document.getElementsByTagName(&quot;html&quot;)[0].classList.add(&quot;dark&quot;)
        } else {
            document.getElementsByTagName(&quot;html&quot;)[0].classList.remove(&quot;dark&quot;)
        }
    }, [])

    useEffect(() =&gt; {
        if (theme == &quot;dark&quot;) {
            document.getElementsByTagName(&quot;html&quot;)[0].classList.add(&quot;dark&quot;)

            localStorage.theme = &quot;dark&quot;
        } else {
            document.getElementsByTagName(&quot;html&quot;)[0].classList.remove(&quot;dark&quot;)

            localStorage.theme = &quot;light&quot;
        }
    }, [theme])

    const toggleDarkMode = () =&gt; {
        if (theme == &quot;dark&quot;) {
            setTheme(&quot;light&quot;)
        } else {
            setTheme(&quot;dark&quot;)
        }
    }

    return (
        &lt;button onClick={toggleDarkMode}&gt;
            {theme === &quot;light&quot; ? (
                &lt;WiDaySunny style={{ color: &quot;black&quot; }} /&gt;
            ) : (
                &lt;MdOutlineDarkMode style={{ color: &quot;white&quot; }} /&gt;
            )}
        &lt;/button&gt;
    )
}

export default mode
</code></pre>
<p>Let's add a touch of fun, we could also switch between themes by using our keyboard buttons by adding listeners, obviously this wouldn't work for mobile devices. To implement this we'd need to add an extra function in our <code>theme.js</code> file which would detect keys pressed.</p>
<pre><code class="language-js">useEffect(() =&gt; {

document.addEventListener(&quot;keydown&quot;, detectKeydown, true)

}, [])

const detectKeydown = (e) =&gt; {
// on pressing ctlr + d or ctlr + l our theme would be switched.
if (e.key === &quot;d&quot; &amp;&amp; (e.ctrlKey || e.metaKey) || (e.key === &quot;l&quot; &amp;&amp; (e.ctrlKey || e.metaKey) )) {

toggleDarkMode()

}
</code></pre>
<p>Finally, we'd do some bit of styling work on our css</p>
<pre><code class="language-css">:root {
    --text-color: #3a333d;
    --background: #fff;
}

.light {
    --text-color: #3a333d;
    --background: #fff;
}

.dark {
    --text-color: #bbbbbb;
    --background: #000;
}
</code></pre>
<p>And with all this set up, you should have a theme working fine on your react app.</p>
<hr>
<p>[^1]:
<a href="https://medium.com/jspoint/a-beginners-guide-to-react-server-side-rendering-ssr-bf3853841d55">Server Side Rendering: A method of rendering pages which generates the HTML on the server for the all page but only <strong>on the first load</strong></a></p>
<pre><code>[^2]: [Static Site Generation a.k.a. SSG is pre-rendering your React app into HTML at build time.](https://dev.to/anshuman_bhardwaj/what-the-heck-is-ssg-static-site-generation-explained-with-nextjs-5cja).
</code></pre>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Leo Tolstoy]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/tolstoy</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/tolstoy</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Leo is more than an ordinary writer, he is more of a religious thinker, a moral crusader and an inspirational predecessor of pacific protesters like Mahatma Ghandi .]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Leo Tolstoy is an emblematic figure in the history of a nation celebrated for its cultural achievements, one of the two or three contenders for the title of Russia's greatest writters.
Since the beginning of the year 2022, I have found a profund and uplifting experience whilst reading the great work of art and literature written by Lev Nikolayevich Tolstoy popularly known as Leo Tostoy. I have been immersely impacted by his style of writing, the patterns of his thoughts, simplicity and subtleness in words.</p>
<p>To me, Leo is more than an ordinary writer, he is more of a religious thinker, a moral crusader and an inspirational predecessor of pacific protesters like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahatma_Gandhi">Mahatma Ghandi</a> .</p>
<h3>Search For Religious Truth And Moral Purity</h3>
<p>On completion of Leo's two masterpiece <strong>Ana Karenina</strong> and <strong>War and Peace</strong>, he spent eventless decades in his home where he became obsessed with a search for religious truth and moral purity, setting unattainable goals of righteousness for himself and his audience.</p>
<p>Leo dominated his thinking until the moment of his death by writings of a Genevan philosopher and political thinker <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Jacques_Rousseau">Jean-Jacques Rousseau</a> who belived that human babies are born into natural state of goodness, only to be corrupted by education, inequality and immorality, a process which explains our lapses into bad behaviour.</p>
<p>The wonder is that the best of Leo's published works travels in opposite direction compared to the ideas Rousseau. War and Peace is nothing but an affirmation of life.</p>
<p>Sadly, Leo died in 1910 at the age of 82, though the residue of his remarkable literature has long lived till this day which has now gained an unforgettable honor around the world</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Everyone thinks of changing the world, but no one thinks of changing himself.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Respect was invented to cover the empty place where love should be.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If you look for perfection, you'll never be content.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“We lost because we told ourselves we lost.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Boredom: the desire for desires.”</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>