<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Saheed's Second Brain</title>
        <link>https://saheed.codes/</link>
        <description>Ahmed Saheed's Encyclopedia | Second Brain</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 13:26:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>Feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>© Ahmed Saheed 2022</copyright>
        <category>Second Brain</category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Asymptotic Analysis]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/asymptotic</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/asymptotic</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[growth of a runtime/rate of growth of an algorithm without worrying about different computers , compilers or implementation.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
Because the time taken to perform an algorithms differs due to input size, compilers, computer language & hardware, they are not efficiently calculated using methods like benchmarking or mere assumptions. **This is where asymptotic analysis comes in:**

During asymptotic analysis we do not really calculate time as said earlier, instead we calculate the amount of operations in the [algorithm](/second-brain/algorithm) because we expect performance “time” to be dependant on both **size of input** and machine power. ([Refer to khan material for better explanation](https://www.khanacademy.org/computing/computer-science/algorithms/asymptotic-notation/a/asymptotic-notation)).

Formal Definition: It is a way of describing **growth of a runtime/rate of growth** of an algorithm without worrying about different computers , compilers or implementation.

### Asymptotic Notations

1.  BigO notation ⇒ Upper Bound

2.  Omega ⇒ Lower Bound

3.  Theta ⇒ Both upper and lower bound also called tight bound.

### Further Reading

-   [Big0 Cheat Sheet](https://www.bigocheatsheet.com/)

-   [MIT Asymptotic Analysis Recitation 2011](http://courses.csail.mit.edu/6.006/spring11/rec/rec01.pdf)

-   [More consise explanation of time complexities](<https://medium.com/swlh/big-o-notation-and-time-space-complexity-1806936e6330#:~:text=O(nlogn)%20is%20known%20as,using%20O(logn)%20space.>)
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cities And Ambibtion]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/cities-ambition</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/cities-ambition</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[An essay by Paul Graham which i am obliged keep]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
### An essay by Paul Graham which i am obliged keep

Great cities attract ambitious people. You can sense it when you walk around one. In a hundred subtle ways, the city sends you a message: you could do more; you should try harder.

The surprising thing is how different these messages can be. New York tells you, above all: you should make more money. There are other messages too, of course. You should be hipper. You should be better looking. But the clearest message is that you should be richer.

What I like about Boston (or rather Cambridge) is that the message there is: you should be smarter. You really should get around to reading all those books you've been meaning to.

When you ask what message a city sends, you sometimes get surprising answers. As much as they respect brains in Silicon Valley, the message the Valley sends is: you should be more powerful.

That's not quite the same message New York sends. Power matters in New York too of course, but New York is pretty impressed by a billion dollars even if you merely inherited it. In Silicon Valley no one would care except a few real estate agents. What matters in Silicon Valley is how much effect you have on the world. The reason people there care about Larry and Sergey is not their wealth but the fact that they control Google, which affects practically everyone.

---

How much does it matter what message a city sends? Empirically, the answer seems to be: a lot. You might think that if you had enough strength of mind to do great things, you'd be able to transcend your environment. Where you live should make at most a couple percent difference. But if you look at the historical evidence, it seems to matter more than that. Most people who did great things were clumped together in a few places where that sort of thing was done at the time.

You can see how powerful cities are from the case of the Milanese Leonardo. Practically every fifteenth century Italian painter you've heard of was from Florence, even though Milan was just as big. People in Florence weren't genetically different, so you have to assume there was someone born in Milan with as much natural ability as Leonardo. What happened to him?

If even someone with the same natural ability as Leonardo couldn't beat the force of environment, do you suppose you can?

I don't. I'm fairly stubborn, but I wouldn't try to fight this force. I'd rather use it. So I've thought a lot about where to live.

I'd always imagined Berkeley would be the ideal place — that it would basically be Cambridge with good weather. But when I finally tried living there a couple years ago, it turned out not to be. The message Berkeley sends is: you should live better. Life in Berkeley is very civilized. It's probably the place in America where someone from Northern Europe would feel most at home. But it's not humming with ambition.

In retrospect it shouldn't have been surprising that a place so pleasant would attract people interested above all in quality of life. Cambridge with good weather, it turns out, is not Cambridge. The people you find in Cambridge are not there by accident. You have to make sacrifices to live there. It's expensive and somewhat grubby, and the weather's often bad. So the kind of people you find in Cambridge are the kind of people who want to live where the smartest people are, even if that means living in an expensive, grubby place with bad weather.

As of this writing, Cambridge seems to be the intellectual capital of the world. I realize that seems a preposterous claim. What makes it true is that it's more preposterous to claim about anywhere else. American universities currently seem to be the best, judging from the flow of ambitious students. And what US city has a stronger claim? New York? A fair number of smart people, but diluted by a much larger number of neanderthals in suits. The Bay Area has a lot of smart people too, but again, diluted; there are two great universities, but they're far apart. Harvard and MIT are practically adjacent by West Coast standards, and they're surrounded by about 20 other colleges and universities. [^1]

Cambridge as a result feels like a town whose main industry is ideas, while New York's is finance and Silicon Valley's is startups.

---

When you talk about cities in the sense we are, what you're really talking about is collections of people. For a long time cities were the only large collections of people, so you could use the two ideas interchangeably. But we can see how much things are changing from the examples I've mentioned. New York is a classic great city. But Cambridge is just part of a city, and Silicon Valley is not even that. (San Jose is not, as it sometimes claims, the capital of Silicon Valley. It's just 178 square miles at one end of it.)

Maybe the Internet will change things further. Maybe one day the most important community you belong to will be a virtual one, and it won't matter where you live physically. But I wouldn't bet on it. The physical world is very high bandwidth, and some of the ways cities send you messages are quite subtle.

One of the exhilarating things about coming back to Cambridge every spring is walking through the streets at dusk, when you can see into the houses. When you walk through Palo Alto in the evening, you see nothing but the blue glow of TVs. In Cambridge you see shelves full of promising-looking books. Palo Alto was probably much like Cambridge in 1960, but you'd never guess now that there was a university nearby. Now it's just one of the richer neighborhoods in Silicon Valley. [^2]

A city speaks to you mostly by accident — in things you see through windows, in conversations you overhear. It's not something you have to seek out, but something you can't turn off. One of the occupational hazards of living in Cambridge is overhearing the conversations of people who use interrogative intonation in declarative sentences. But on average I'll take Cambridge conversations over New York or Silicon Valley ones.

A friend who moved to Silicon Valley in the late 90s said the worst thing about living there was the low quality of the eavesdropping. At the time I thought she was being deliberately eccentric. Sure, it can be interesting to eavesdrop on people, but is good quality eavesdropping so important that it would affect where you chose to live? Now I understand what she meant. The conversations you overhear tell you what sort of people you're among.

---

> No matter how determined you are, it's hard not to be influenced by the people around you. It's not so much that you do whatever a city expects of you, but that you get discouraged when no one around you cares about the same things you do.

There's an imbalance between encouragement and discouragement like that between gaining and losing money. Most people overvalue negative amounts of money: they'll work much harder to avoid losing a dollar than to gain one. Similarly, although there are plenty of people strong enough to resist doing something just because that's what one is supposed to do where they happen to be, there are few strong enough to keep working on something no one around them cares about.

Because ambitions are to some extent incompatible and admiration is a zero-sum game, each city tends to focus on one type of ambition. The reason Cambridge is the intellectual capital is not just that there's a concentration of smart people there, but that there's nothing *else* people there care about more. Professors in New York and the Bay area are second class citizens — till they start hedge funds or startups respectively.

This suggests an answer to a question people in New York have wondered about since the Bubble: whether New York could grow into a startup hub to rival Silicon Valley. One reason that's unlikely is that someone starting a startup in New York would feel like a second class citizen. [^3] There's already something else people in New York admire more.

In the long term, that could be a bad thing for New York. The power of an important new technology does eventually convert to money. So by caring more about money and less about power than Silicon Valley, New York is recognizing the same thing, but slower. [^4] And in fact it has been losing to Silicon Valley at its own game: the ratio of New York to California residents in the Forbes 400 has decreased from 1.45 (81:56) when the list was first published in 1982 to .83 (73:88) in 2007.

---

Not all cities send a message. Only those that are centers for some type of ambition do. And it can be hard to tell exactly what message a city sends without living there. I understand the messages of New York, Cambridge, and Silicon Valley because I've lived for several years in each of them. DC and LA seem to send messages too, but I haven't spent long enough in either to say for sure what they are.

The big thing in LA seems to be fame. There's an A List of people who are most in demand right now, and what's most admired is to be on it, or friends with those who are. Beneath that, the message is much like New York's, though perhaps with more emphasis on physical attractiveness.

In DC the message seems to be that the most important thing is who you know. You want to be an insider. In practice this seems to work much as in LA. There's an A List and you want to be on it or close to those who are. The only difference is how the A List is selected. And even that is not that different.

At the moment, San Francisco's message seems to be the same as Berkeley's: you should live better. But this will change if enough startups choose SF over the Valley. During the Bubble that was a predictor of failure — a self-indulgent choice, like buying expensive office furniture. Even now I'm suspicious when startups choose SF. But if enough good ones do, it stops being a self-indulgent choice, because the center of gravity of Silicon Valley will shift there.

I haven't found anything like Cambridge for intellectual ambition. Oxford and Cambridge (England) feel like Ithaca or Hanover: the message is there, but not as strong.

Paris was once a great intellectual center. If you went there in 1300, it might have sent the message Cambridge does now. But I tried living there for a bit last year, and the ambitions of the inhabitants are not intellectual ones. The message Paris sends now is: do things with style. I liked that, actually. Paris is the only city I've lived in where people genuinely cared about art. In America only a few rich people buy original art, and even the more sophisticated ones rarely get past judging it by the brand name of the artist. But looking through windows at dusk in Paris you can see that people there actually care what paintings look like. Visually, Paris has the best eavesdropping I know. [^5]

There's one more message I've heard from cities: in London you can still (barely) hear the message that one should be more aristocratic. If you listen for it you can also hear it in Paris, New York, and Boston. But this message is everywhere very faint. It would have been strong 100 years ago, but now I probably wouldn't have picked it up at all if I hadn't deliberately tuned in to that wavelength to see if there was any signal left.

---

So far the complete list of messages I've picked up from cities is: wealth, style, hipness, physical attractiveness, fame, political power, economic power, intelligence, social class, and quality of life.

My immediate reaction to this list is that it makes me slightly queasy. I'd always considered ambition a good thing, but I realize now that was because I'd always implicitly understood it to mean ambition in the areas I cared about. When you list everything ambitious people are ambitious about, it's not so pretty.

On closer examination I see a couple things on the list that are surprising in the light of history. For example, physical attractiveness wouldn't have been there 100 years ago (though it might have been 2400 years ago). It has always mattered for women, but in the late twentieth century it seems to have started to matter for men as well. I'm not sure why — probably some combination of the increasing power of women, the increasing influence of actors as models, and the fact that so many people work in offices now: you can't show off by wearing clothes too fancy to wear in a factory, so you have to show off with your body instead.

Hipness is another thing you wouldn't have seen on the list 100 years ago. Or wouldn't you? What it means is to know what's what. So maybe it has simply replaced the component of social class that consisted of being "au fait." That could explain why hipness seems particularly admired in London: it's version 2 of the traditional English delight in obscure codes that only insiders understand.

Economic power would have been on the list 100 years ago, but what we mean by it is changing. It used to mean the control of vast human and material resources. But increasingly it means the ability to direct the course of technology, and some of the people in a position to do that are not even rich — leaders of important open source projects, for example. The Captains of Industry of times past had laboratories full of clever people cooking up new technologies for them. The new breed are themselves those people.

As this force gets more attention, another is dropping off the list: social class. I think the two changes are related. Economic power, wealth, and social class are just names for the same thing at different stages in its life: economic power converts to wealth, and wealth to social class. So the focus of admiration is simply shifting upstream.

---

Does anyone who wants to do great work have to live in a great city? No; all great cities inspire some sort of ambition, but they aren't the only places that do. For some kinds of work, all you need is a handful of talented colleagues.

What cities provide is an audience, and a funnel for peers. These aren't so critical in something like math or physics, where no audience matters except your peers, and judging ability is sufficiently straightforward that hiring and admissions committees can do it reliably. In a field like math or physics all you need is a department with the right colleagues in it. It could be anywhere — in Los Alamos, New Mexico, for example.

It's in fields like the arts or writing or technology that the larger environment matters. In these the best practitioners aren't conveniently collected in a few top university departments and research labs — partly because talent is harder to judge, and partly because people pay for these things, so one doesn't need to rely on teaching or research funding to support oneself. It's in these more chaotic fields that it helps most to be in a great city: you need the encouragement of feeling that people around you care about the kind of work you do, and since you have to find peers for yourself, you need the much larger intake mechanism of a great city.

You don't have to live in a great city your whole life to benefit from it. The critical years seem to be the early and middle ones of your career. Clearly you don't have to grow up in a great city. Nor does it seem to matter if you go to college in one. To most college students a world of a few thousand people seems big enough. Plus in college you don't yet have to face the hardest kind of work — discovering new problems to solve.

It's when you move on to the next and much harder step that it helps most to be in a place where you can find peers and encouragement. You seem to be able to leave, if you want, once you've found both. The Impressionists show the typical pattern: they were born all over France (Pissarro was born in the Carribbean) and died all over France, but what defined them were the years they spent together in Paris.

---

Unless you're sure what you want to do and where the leading center for it is, your best bet is probably to try living in several places when you're young. You can never tell what message a city sends till you live there, or even whether it still sends one. Often your information will be wrong: I tried living in Florence when I was 25, thinking it would be an art center, but it turned out I was 450 years too late.

Even when a city is still a live center of ambition, you won't know for sure whether its message will resonate with you till you hear it. When I moved to New York, I was very excited at first. It's an exciting place. So it took me quite a while to realize I just wasn't like the people there. I kept searching for the Cambridge of New York. It turned out it was way, way uptown: an hour uptown by air.

Some people know at 16 what sort of work they're going to do, but in most ambitious kids, ambition seems to precede anything specific to be ambitious about. They know they want to do something great. They just haven't decided yet whether they're going to be a rock star or a brain surgeon. There's nothing wrong with that. But it means if you have this most common type of ambition, you'll probably have to figure out where to live by trial and error. You'll probably have to find the city where you feel at home to know what sort of ambition you have.

[^1]: This is one of the advantages of not having the universities in your country controlled by the government. When governments decide how to allocate resources, political deal-making causes things to be spread out geographically. No central goverment would put its two best universities in the same town, unless it was the capital (which would cause other problems). But scholars seem to like to cluster together as much as people in any other field, and when given the freedom to they derive the same advantages from it.
[^2]: There are still a few old professors in Palo Alto, but one by one they die and their houses are transformed by developers into McMansions and sold to VPs of Bus Dev.
[^3]: How many times have you read about startup founders who continued to live inexpensively as their companies took off? Who continued to dress in jeans and t-shirts, to drive the old car they had in grad school, and so on? If you did that in New York, people would treat you like shit. If you walk into a fancy restaurant in San Francisco wearing a jeans and a t-shirt, they're nice to you; who knows who you might be? Not in New York. One sign of a city's potential as a technology center is the number of restaurants that still require jackets for men. According to Zagat's there are none in San Francisco, LA, Boston, or Seattle, 4 in DC, 6 in Chicago, 8 in London, 13 in New York, and 20 in Paris. (Zagat's lists the Ritz Carlton Dining Room in SF as requiring jackets but I couldn't believe it, so I called to check and in fact they don't. Apparently there's only one restaurant left on the entire West Coast that still requires jackets: The French Laundry in Napa Valley.)
[^4]: Ideas are one step upstream from economic power, so it's conceivable that intellectual centers like Cambridge will one day have an edge over Silicon Valley like the one the Valley has over New York. This seems unlikely at the moment; if anything Boston is falling further and further behind. The only reason I even mention the possibility is that the path from ideas to startups has recently been getting smoother. It's a lot easier now for a couple of hackers with no business experience to start a startup than it was 10 years ago. If you extrapolate another 20 years, maybe the balance of power will start to shift back. I wouldn't bet on it, but I wouldn't bet against it either.
[^5]: If Paris is where people care most about art, why is New York the center of gravity of the art business? Because in the twentieth century, art as brand split apart from art as stuff. New York is where the richest buyers are, but all they demand from art is brand, and since you can base brand on anything with a sufficiently identifiable style, you may as well use the local stuff.
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Javari]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/javari</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/javari</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A modern day version of Christ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[

God is real and he using me for a bigger purpose  
So fuck the world that would have you think that a nigga is  worthless

Sometimes I think that these verses can help a person  
way more than the ones they reading in churches on days of worship .

No disrespect to the Lord and Savior, that ain't just ego. I just observe that them words no longer relate to people because  modern times are flooded with dollar signs.
And social media stunting, most niggas just wanna shine.

They frame of mind so far removed from the days and times of Nazareth. Life these days is a labyrinth, in a maze so elaborate we barely get through half of it before it's too late.

All of that to say maybe the hood need a new faith  
A new story about a boy from not too far where you stay

---


His momma was a virgin named Yolanda  
And she raised him on her own, after she was disowned. 
Her momma called her a liar, said "Get the fuck out my home"  
Since you wanna be grown  
So, there she was now, seventeen and alone.

But this lil' boy that grew in her stomach made her feel strong  
The angels paid her a visit one night and let it be known  
This was God's child, woman behold the miracle.  
She shed tears 'cause she never believed in a spiritual  
But her heart was pure and she was good  
For eighteen years she raised him on Section 8 in the cold embrace of the hood. 
Did the best as she could, the boy was named Javari  
Walked with the spirit of his father emanating from body.

---

Back in the hood, look at lil' Vari preach  
His words were full of spirit, his truth it would always reach  
He laid his hands on Toya, when niggas called her a freak  
And told her that God loved her no matter who she let beat

But being promiscuous is a sign that there's something deep  
That troubles her soul, the day she lets it go, she'll find peace  
She broke down admitting her stepfather had touched her for years  
She kept it secret for fear of her mother's grief  
Now the bitterness she feels for that nigga is at a peak  
And her lack of self-esteem is the reason that she would sleep with anybody

And not think twice, Javari spoke calmly  
Instructing her to forgive her stepfather  
Though he was wrong he was sick  
Afflicted by evil, but the power to switch  
How you feel about people who hurt you is truly a gift  
The thing that can make you rich or keep you down in a ditch  
If you refuse to let go of the ground, then how can you lift?  
Into the sky where you belong with the most high  
Now wipe those tears from your eyes, my father wants you to fly.

---

Back in the hood, Javari built up a following  
Niggas put down they pistols eventually  
And stopped swallowing molly pills Instead their bodies filled with spirit  
Twelve lil' homies soaking up every word that they hearing

The neighborhood changed in attitude and appearance  
Police dumbfounded by lack of crime and they swear it's a fluke  
Not knowing the truth, that this a miracle  
Niggas is waking up with the powers that be they fearing

---

So government keep a tap on Javari and those who practice adherence  
To things he teaching and then comes to interference

They stormed the hood, guns out  
Bust into the house that he slept in  
A warrant claiming suspicion of drug possession  
But Vari sat calmly as if he had been expecting  
Heart full of love, even for those who need to oppress him

They told him "Hands up" and he did just as they directed  
They fired on him, claiming they thought he reached for a weapon  
He laid on the floor breathless, blood leaking from his chest

Plus a bullet-hole through both of his palms, ain't that a message?

---

The neighborhood was stressing 
The son of God murdered and carried away on stretcher by the oppressor.

Three days later, the coroner pulled the table  
And what happened next is like somethin' you see on cable or hear in a fable

He was suddenly able to open his eyes, look at him rise, the coroner was surprised  
Without a word Javari walked out, went straight to the hood  
The people couldn't believe it, they froze right where they stood

As he walked by, God flowin' from every inch of his frame  
He said "Hear me out my niggas, let me be your proof, my father is real  
And through love, homie, peace can be found I died for you, so that one day you would be able to see you a child of God, just like me"]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Letter to my future self]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/letter-to-myself</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/letter-to-myself</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A ponder on my past, present and future]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[

### Hi Saheed,

This letter goes from my current self to my future self. I am currently writing from a dining table after having a hot bowl of noodles while listening to a chakra meditation sound. You might someday be reading this at a different place, in a different time doing absoluetly something else. 

I haven't written such a letter like this throughout my existence, but i'd try to make it organic as possible. 

![](https://i.pinimg.com/originals/58/aa/64/58aa641cfe646b0c17972ccc5c312989.jpg)


---

To begin,  i'd need to rewind a bit to your last days of secondary school. I think this letter would be absolutely incomplete without that flashback. 

### Early 2019

At that point your life felt abysmal and lacked meaning, You had just gotten into SS3 the final point of the Nigerian Secondary Education system. This was one of the most memorable moments of your life. You were quite young then  perphaps 15 or 16yo, getting ready for college and  embedding into your brain your then assumed imagination of a college student. At that age you hadn't understood anything about your thought process, You only did whatever you felt would please your peers irrespective of your parent words which were considered a burden. You lived in a very delusional and detestable bubble called life. Things really went fast! You eventually encircled yourself with a very wrong set of individuals which you looked up to and called your friends.

Time went by, and things got worst. You'd started using drugs, forgotten the nostalgic childhood dream of becoming an astronaut. Your imagination of being in a space suit, wandering the moon and being the like of  Dr. Ben Carson had suddenly been swallowed by this darkness within your inner self. What had really happended? Can you recall? 

This irrational way of life lasted a while and your parent started questioning. They became quite worried, the darkeness was visible around your dads conjunctiva. What and where have i done wrong were questions he asked himself. He felt terribly sad and you knew it. But you were to busy apeasing your so called friends!

---

### Late 2019

You'd finally graduated and a magnanimous graduation party was thrown for you, It wasn't necessary, but it was done none the less at the expense of your parent. Your grades wasn't excellent neither was it up to expectations but your parents still accepted it. 

Graduation had come to an end, all of your collegues and friends had moved on and splitted all around the country. You remained home waiting to be admitted into a university. Your parent ran helter-skelter to make sure you'd gotten accepted in your desired university, all to no avail. 

But your ill habits remained and needed to be sustained. You took forcefully from your parent purse. You felt this wasn't anything wrong besides it's for your parent! This continued till they couldn't take it any longer and became enraged by your attitude, your appearance and your way of life as a whole. You lacked  sense of remourse and empathy due to your emotional numbness caused by this sickness.

Now you hadn't heard from any university yet and you felt stuck in a chasm between your current illusion and reality. You became self aware but couldn't help it.  Your parents where still willing to help. They lamented though but never left your side, they always wanted the best. You ended up in a mental facility.

You had settled in quite nicely in this new place, feeling serene and a stong sense of calm being far away from the hustle and bustle of the outer world. The inhabitants had shown you love, kindness and affection irrespective of some random arguements from time to time. Some were quite educated, others lay men but the majority was soldiers.

You'd been clean for a while now, spending time reading books like [the road less travelled](https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/347852.The_Road_Less_Traveled) and [Abnormal Psychology](https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/773020.Abnormal_Psychology), playing card game, table tennis and experimenting with psycho therapy.

You'd made friends with some really smart fellows like Dr Abdul-Salam, Dr Chineye , Uche the American college [dean enlisted](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean%27s_list) dropout who i was greatly influenced by and the Civil Engineering graduate from University of Lagos.

---

### Early & Mid 2020

You had been allowed to leave this facility because you had to resume college at University of Lagos. Prior to resumption you'd been warned about relapse by both your therapist and your parents, your dad in particular. You'd also promised not to let them down.

Weeks went by as a freshman in college, you were doing great, not until you met some of your old peers from secondary school and decided to let yourself and loved once abashed and conscience-stricken.

This relapse was beyond your belief and far-fetched. It left you emotionally distorted. Those old darkness started creeping their way back into your life and this time eating deep into your endocardium. Your actions were outside your cognitive comprehension. It sucked and you knew it ! You felt like a swineherd returning to a pigsty immediately after taking hot shower.


---



### Late 2020
You'd become intolerable by your parent and your actions became notable and detesteble by the society around.

You decided to leave, perhaps it felt unbearable after what happend the afternoon you departed home. You weren't ready to feel any sort of remorse, instead you sought fault in your loved once and your upbringing. Delaying gratification and shying away from your reality. You were realistically disgusting and highly loathed!

You left, perphaps dad got back from work asking where you were or he was called that same moment of you departure, who knows. I wonder how he spent that night. Perphas so pained, he layed awake all night wiping the tears that rolled down his cheeks. 

You'd decided to trade your comfort, satiety, education and most importantly your loved ones for an absolutely nonworthy cause. You accepted your own self made lies!

None the less he still came looking for you. He loved you down to earth! He saw something positively distinct and clearcut about you. 

With a leap of fate, he believed in you and sent you 3,198 miles away from home for enquire quality education and pursue a better life. He begged not to be disappointed. 

---

### 2021 Starting Anew

![](https://i.pinimg.com/originals/b9/09/6c/b9096cf99af608099092505cefd2dd96.jpg)

I ended up in Europe, unbelievable! i took awhile to to clearly grasp the message ([cities-ambition](/second-brain/cities-ambition)) of this new society. I felt a bit overwhelmed at first about the protrayed solemnity of my new settlement, it felt absolutely contrary to what i was used to.

Time passed, I'd started a new school, settled in nicely and remained alone, not out of choice but out of fear for having wrong friends again and going down the old route i'd just miraculously escaped.

Lectures at school initially felt like a conundrum. I had decided to take Computer Science which deep down i'm very capable of handling. I felt very defeated by the workload but never let go. I struggled and couragously passed my first exam in europe.

### 2022




Away from the madding crowd, living a silent life in the age of noise, i've fellen in love with [books](/books) and [programming](https://github.com/ahmedsaheed) also mountaineering but haven't had a chance to climb on yet. 

I've grown alot also learnt a reasonable amount of stuff.  I turned 19yo few months ago! I really wonder how time passes bye so fast. The transformation in my life over a couple of years has left me perplexed. I have acquired a more broaden and enlightened view of myself and the larger society. 

Enough time has been spent pondering on my true self. i.e who i am now and who i want to really be. I have found the subtleness in self love and societal good. I have also outlined some noticable flaws to be worked on. Most of these are easier said than done, but deep down it's for nobody except oneself. 

> I currently see myself as a sailor and my body as a ship. This ship sails on an ocean consisting of all sort of things. My job as a sailor is to protect this ship from sinking at all cost. Making it sacred and safe from danger.

I would keep writing to you more often in absolute honesty. 
I hope you're doing exceptionally well whenever you read this.

Yours truthfully, 
Ahmed.




















]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Quotes]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/quotes</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/quotes</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Some quote to live by]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
### Some quote to live by

> I am persuaded that normal human beings are biologically built for an activity that is aimed towards a goal and that idleness, or aimless work gives rise to suffering and to entropy
 - Primo Levi
 
 
 > We took risks, we knew we took them; things have come against us, and therefore we have no cause to complain, but bow to the will of providence, determined still to do our best to the last
  - Robert Falcon Scott

> The one great advantage which inexperience confers on an amateur is that he is not bogged down by the tradition or precedence. To him, all things appears simple and he chooses straightforward solutions to the problem he faces. Often, of cause, it defeats the sucess his seeking, and sometimes it has tragic results, but the man himself doesn't know this when he sets out on his adventure
- Walt Unsworth 

> But there are some men for whom the unattanable has a special attraction. Usually they are not experts: their ambition and fantasies are strong enough to brush aside the doubt which more cautious men might have. Determination and faith are their strongest weapons. At best such men are regarded as eccentric; at worst, mad ...
- Walt Unsworth 

> The more impropable the situation and the greater the demand on a man, the more sweetly his blood flows later in release from all the tension. The possiblity of danger serves merely to sharpen his awareness and control. And perphas this is rationale to all risky activities: You delibrately raise the ante of effort and concentration in order, as its were, to clear your mind of all trivialities.
- A. Alvarez

 >It is a fundamental law of nature that to evolve one has to push one’s limits, which is painful, in order to gain strength—whether it’s in the form of lifting weights, facing problems head-on, or in any other way. Nature gave us pain as a messaging device to tell us that we are approaching, or that we have exceeded, our limits in some way. At the same time, nature made the process of getting stronger require us to push our limits. Gaining strength is the adaptation process of the body and the mind to encountering one’s limits, which is painful. In other words, both pain and strength typically result from encountering one’s barriers. When we encounter pain, we are at an important juncture in our decision-making process
- Ray Dalio]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Theming In React]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/react-theming</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/react-theming</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Theming isn't that tricky!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
Lately, the use of multiple themes on web and mobile applications has risen immersely. While developing this website, I struggled during implementation this feature.

I have decided to write this brief note on next js and react theming.

There are many ways to implement theming in react, but I have decided to explain two only.

### prerequisite

I assert you already have a react environment to work with, if not you can easily create one using:

```bash
npx create-next-app@latest
```

or

```bash
npx create-react-app my-app
```

### Implementing the theming.

First Approaching - using the [next theme libary](https://github.com/pacocoursey/next-themes)

You'd need to add the libary to your project:

```bash
$ npm install next-themes
# or
$ yarn add next-themes
```

In your `pages/_app.js` file, you'd need to add the following line:

```js
import { ThemeProvider } from "next-themes"

function MyApp({ Component, pageProps }) {
    return (
        <ThemeProvider>
            <Component {...pageProps} />
        </ThemeProvider>
    )
}

export default MyApp
```

Then implement your style

```css
:root {
    /* Your default theme */
    --background: white;
    --foreground: black;
}

[data-theme="dark"] {
    --background: black;
    --foreground: white;
}
```

Lastly, create a theme button component in your `components/theme-button.js` file:

```js
import { createContext, useEffect } from "react"
import { WiDaySunny } from "react-icons/wi"
import { MdOutlineDarkMode } from "react-icons/md"
import { useTheme } from "next-themes"

const mode = () => {
    const { theme, setTheme } = useTheme()
    const toggleDarkMode = () => {
        if (theme == "light") {
            setTheme("dark")
        } else {
            setTheme("light")
        }
    }

    return (
        <div>
            <button onClick={toggleDarkMode}>
                {theme === "light" ? (
                    <WiDaySunny style={{ color: "black" }} />
                ) : (
                    <MdOutlineDarkMode style={{ color: "white" }} />
                )}
            </button>
        </div>
    )
}

export default mode
```

Second Approach - Implement the theming yourself.

Before we begin, we'd make use of react hook [`useLocalStorage`](https://usehooks.com/useLocalStorage/) which stores the users selected theme in local storage so that it persists through a page refresh.

We'd Also need our theme colors and element specified out in our stylesheet.

And with all these basic stuff out, we're good to go!

To begin, create a `hooks` folder in your root directory. Add a new javascript file in the directory like so `useLocalStorage.js`.

Now in your `useLocalStorage.js` file lets add some code to allow SSR[^1] and SSG[^2] work decently.

```js
import { useState } from "react"

export function useLocalStorage(key, initialValue) {
    const [storedValue, setStoredValue] = useState(() => {
        if (typeof window === "undefined") {
            return initialValue
        }
        try {
            // Get from local storage by key
            const item = window.localStorage.getItem(key)
            // Parse stored json or if none return initialValue
            return item ? JSON.parse(item) : initialValue
        } catch (error) {
            // If error also return initialValue
            console.log(error)
            return initialValue
        }
    })
    const setValue = (value) => {
        try {
            // Allow value to be a function so we have same API as useState
            const valueToStore = value instanceof Function ? value(storedValue) : value
            // Save state
            setStoredValue(valueToStore)
            // Save to local storage
            if (typeof window !== "undefined") {
                window.localStorage.setItem(key, JSON.stringify(valueToStore))
            }
        } catch (error) {
            // A more advanced implementation would handle the error case
            console.log(error)
        }
    }
    return [storedValue, setValue]
}
```

On completion of the hook, we'll need to implement a function which makes our theming work.

Implementing this is fairly easy when done correctly.
To get started let's create a component called `theme.js` in our component's folder. In our `theme.js` file lets implement this function

```js
import { createContext, useEffect } from "react"
import { useLocalStorage } from "../hooks/useLocalStorage"
import { WiDaySunny } from "react-icons/wi"
import { MdOutlineDarkMode } from "react-icons/md"

function mode() {
    const [theme, setTheme] = useLocalStorage("theme", "light")

    useEffect(() => {
        if (
            localStorage.theme === "dark" ||
            (!("theme" in localStorage) &&
                window.matchMedia("(prefers-color-scheme: dark)").matches)
        ) {
            document.getElementsByTagName("html")[0].classList.add("dark")
        } else {
            document.getElementsByTagName("html")[0].classList.remove("dark")
        }
    }, [])

    useEffect(() => {
        if (theme == "dark") {
            document.getElementsByTagName("html")[0].classList.add("dark")

            localStorage.theme = "dark"
        } else {
            document.getElementsByTagName("html")[0].classList.remove("dark")

            localStorage.theme = "light"
        }
    }, [theme])

    const toggleDarkMode = () => {
        if (theme == "dark") {
            setTheme("light")
        } else {
            setTheme("dark")
        }
    }

    return (
        <button onClick={toggleDarkMode}>
            {theme === "light" ? (
                <WiDaySunny style={{ color: "black" }} />
            ) : (
                <MdOutlineDarkMode style={{ color: "white" }} />
            )}
        </button>
    )
}

export default mode
```

Let's add a touch of fun, we could also switch between themes by using our keyboard buttons by adding listeners, obviously this wouldn't work for mobile devices. To implement this we'd need to add an extra function in our `theme.js` file which would detect keys pressed.

```js
useEffect(() => {

document.addEventListener("keydown", detectKeydown, true)

}, [])

const detectKeydown = (e) => {
// on pressing ctlr + d or ctlr + l our theme would be switched.
if (e.key === "d" && (e.ctrlKey || e.metaKey) || (e.key === "l" && (e.ctrlKey || e.metaKey) )) {

toggleDarkMode()

}
```

Finally, we'd do some bit of styling work on our css

```css
:root {
    --text-color: #3a333d;
    --background: #fff;
}

.light {
    --text-color: #3a333d;
    --background: #fff;
}

.dark {
    --text-color: #bbbbbb;
    --background: #000;
}
```

And with all this set up, you should have a theme working fine on your react app.

---

[^1]:
    [Server Side Rendering: A method of rendering pages which generates the HTML on the server for the all page but only **on the first load**](https://medium.com/jspoint/a-beginners-guide-to-react-server-side-rendering-ssr-bf3853841d55)

    [^2]: [Static Site Generation a.k.a. SSG is pre-rendering your React app into HTML at build time.](https://dev.to/anshuman_bhardwaj/what-the-heck-is-ssg-static-site-generation-explained-with-nextjs-5cja).
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sorting Algorithms]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/sorting-algo</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/sorting-algo</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A sorting algorithm is an algorithm that puts elements of a list into an order]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
Sorting a list of data in ascending, descending, or any order can help both humans and machine sort data efficiently and quickly, perhaps using an algorithm. The sorting algorithms works on data structures of different data types keeping consideration of [asymptotic](/second-brain/asymptotic) analysis.

### Simple Sorting

These algorithms are useful in sorting through data of any type. i.e int, string, object etc. Although the run time of these algorithms are notoriously slow.

1.  Bubble sort
2.  Selection sort
3.  Insertion sort

### Bubble Sort

It is the simplest of all sorting algorithms but very slow.(not advisable for large dataset).

The rules of this algorithms are as follows.

-   Compare only two indexes at a time starting at index the beginning
-   If the LHS is greater than the RHS SWAP positions else do nothing
-   Then, move one position to the right and repeat the previous step.
-   At each stage of the iteration, the largest or greatest element must be on the extreme end of the RHS.
-   Finally repeat all step.

```java

  static void bubbleSort(int[] arr) {
	int temp = 0;
	for(int i=0; i < arr.length; i++){
		for(int j=1; j < (arr.length - i); j++){
		if(arr[j-1] > arr[j]){
//swap elements
			temp = arr[j-1];
			arr[j-1] = arr[j];
			arr[j] = temp;
			} // if close
		} // inner for loop close
	} // outer for loop close
} // end of method

//Time Complexity is mostly = 0(n^2)

```

> The only comparison done here is check if the LHS > RHS. and for each iteration n - 1 is always sorted (where n = length of the array).

### Selection Sort:

It’s a very basic and straight forward way of sorting here are the steps:

1.Scan through the dataset, and locate the smallest date.

1.  Store that smallest date for reference.
2.  If the nothing smaller than what we currently have stored, swap our smallest date to the first index i.e index[0]
3.  Now repeat the above process, this time start scanning from index[i]+1 (because index[i] is already sorted.(where i = currentIndex))
4.  Reiterate the process till you get to the last data which MUST be the largest.

![](https://s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/secure.notion-static.com/f069ac77-d23d-4be8-b4d4-75c1b13803a1/Screenshot_2022-03-01_at_17.43.06.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&X-Amz-Credential=AKIAT73L2G45EIPT3X45%2F20220618%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&X-Amz-Date=20220618T202515Z&X-Amz-Expires=86400&X-Amz-Signature=ba6a02b3f9fe06d2f5d3c7034dabbe946ac5153410dedcaea3c5037b4e6d767a&X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&response-content-disposition=filename%20%3D%22Screenshot%25202022-03-01%2520at%252017.43.06.png%22&x-id=GetObject)

```java
static void selectionSort(int f[]){
	for(int i = 0; i < f.length; i = i + 1){  //iterate through the dataset
		int currMin = i;
		 //storing our current Minimum
		for(int j = i + 1; j < f.length; j = j + 1){
			//repeating the iteration from index[i]+1
			if(f[j] < f[currMin])
					currMin = j;
	}
// swap f[currMin] with f[i]
		int temp = f[i];
		//temporary variable to hold f[i]
		f[i] = f[currMin];
		f[currMin] = temp;
	}
}

//Time Complexity for best & worst case is = 0(n^2)
```

### Insertion Sort

This algorithm is a basic one. Here it’s very similar to sorting a pack of card by hand.

1.  Iterate through the dataset starting at array[1] until array[array.lenght-1].
2.  We’d compare the element at our current position (a.k.a KEY) to it’s predecessors(KEY - 1....).
3.  If the element at current position KEY is smaller that the immediate predecessor, we’d continue the comparison to predecessors after Key immediate predecessor.
4.  Now we’d all those predecessors greater than KEY by one position forward to create space for KEY
5.  We’d insert key into its rightful space.

![](https://s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/secure.notion-static.com/74345031-05e4-4563-8f69-3a9c9f8475c8/Screenshot_2022-03-01_at_18.43.40.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&X-Amz-Credential=AKIAT73L2G45EIPT3X45%2F20220618%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&X-Amz-Date=20220618T203658Z&X-Amz-Expires=86400&X-Amz-Signature=1e084d5f08cc60116b6fbe0e7c4aff323f3622154283830b7e8daeff3f6f8f1a&X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&response-content-disposition=filename%20%3D%22Screenshot%25202022-03-01%2520at%252018.43.40.png%22&x-id=GetObject)

```java
static void insertionSort(int k[]){
		int j = 1;
	while(j < k.length){
		int key = j;
	while(key > 0 && k[key] < k[key-1]){
    int temp = k[key];
		k[key] = k[j-1];
		k[key-1] = temp;
		key = key - 1;
		}
			j = j + 1;
	}
}
```

### Divide & Conquer

Divide and Conquer is an algorithmic paradigm. A typical Divide and Conquer algorithm solves a problem using following three steps.

1.  **Divide**: Break the given problem into subproblems of same type.
2.  **Conquer**: Recursively solve these subproblems
3.  **Combine**: Appropriately combine the answers

### Merge Sort:

In merge sort the divide and conquer paradigm is implemented.

Given: An array **S** to sort, using divide & conquer we’d go this way:

1.  **Divide**: If s.length < 1 return s, because there’s nothing to be sorted. ELSE break the array into two such as S1 and S2, each containing about half of S elements. (i.e s1 has s.length/2 elements & s2 has the remaining s.length/2 elements)
2.  **Conquer**: Here, we’d recursively sort both s1 and s2
3.  **Combine**: Merge the sorted S1 and S2 together to form a sorted S.

![](https://s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/secure.notion-static.com/346cf58d-cff1-43a6-b24e-6a5a496f535c/Screenshot_2022-03-01_at_19.05.01.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&X-Amz-Credential=AKIAT73L2G45EIPT3X45%2F20220618%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&X-Amz-Date=20220618T204209Z&X-Amz-Expires=86400&X-Amz-Signature=4b954e76472003542332bf536e2134eff9ba483da4adc3a628b67238dcf77314&X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&response-content-disposition=filename%20%3D%22Screenshot%25202022-03-01%2520at%252019.05.01.png%22&x-id=GetObject)

```java
static void merge(int f[], int lowerB, int mid, int upperB){
		int i = lowerB;
		int j = mid;
	//use temp array to store merged sub-sequence
	//create a temporary array of size
	//t is initialised to store the index of temp[]
		int temp[] = new int[upperB - lowerB];
		int t = 0;

	//while lowerBound < the middle and middle is also less than upper bound
	// if f[lowerBound] <= f[middle]
	//new array temp should copy all the elements in the lowerBound
	while(i < mid && j < upperB){
		if(f[i] <= f[j]){
			temp[t] = f[i]; i++; t++;
		}
		 //else, temp should copy all the elements in the upper bound
		else{
			temp[t] = f[j]; j++; t++;
	}
}
	//tag on remaining sequence
	//while lowerBound is less that mid
	//the temp array should copy all the elements in the lower bound
	while(i < mid){
		temp[t] = f[i]; i++; t++;
	}
	//while  the middle is less than the upper bound,
	//the temp array should copy all elements from the upper bound
	while(j < upperB){
		temp[t] = f[j]; j++; t++;
	}
	//copy temp back to f
		i = lowerB;
		t = 0;
		while(t < temp.length){
		f[i] = temp[t];
		i++; t++;
	}
}
```

```java
static void mergeSort(int f[], int lowerB, int upperB){
if(lowerB + 1 < upperB){
    int mid = (lowerB + upperB)/2;
    mergeSort(f, lowerB, mid);
    mergeSort(f, mid, upperB);
    merge(f, lowerB, mid, upperB);
  }
}

//Time complexity is 0(nlogn)
```

---

### Further Reading

-   [William Fuset's Sorting Algorithm Implementation](https://github.com/ahmedsaheed/Algorithms/tree/master/src/main/java/com/williamfiset/algorithms/sorting)
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Leo Tolstoy]]></title>
            <link>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/tolstoy</link>
            <guid>https://saheed.codes/second-brain/tolstoy</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Leo is more than an ordinary writer, he is more of a religious thinker, a moral crusader and an inspirational predecessor of pacific protesters like Mahatma Ghandi .]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
Leo Tolstoy is an emblematic figure in the history of a nation celebrated for its cultural achievements, one of the two or three contenders for the title of Russia's greatest writters.
Since the beginning of the year 2022, I have found a profund and uplifting experience whilst reading the great work of art and literature written by Lev Nikolayevich Tolstoy popularly known as Leo Tostoy. I have been immersely impacted by his style of writing, the patterns of his thoughts, simplicity and subtleness in words.

To me, Leo is more than an ordinary writer, he is more of a religious thinker, a moral crusader and an inspirational predecessor of pacific protesters like [Mahatma Ghandi](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahatma_Gandhi) .


### Search For Religious Truth And Moral Purity

On completion of Leo's two masterpiece **Ana Karenina** and **War and Peace**, he spent eventless decades in his home where he became obsessed with a search for religious truth and moral purity, setting unattainable goals of righteousness for himself and his audience.

Leo dominated his thinking until the moment of his death by writings of a Genevan philosopher and political thinker [Jean-Jacques Rousseau](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Jacques_Rousseau) who belived that human babies are born into natural state of goodness, only to be corrupted by education, inequality and immorality, a process which explains our lapses into bad behaviour.

The wonder is that the best of Leo's published works travels in opposite direction compared to the ideas Rousseau. War and Peace is nothing but an affirmation of life.

Sadly, Leo died in 1910 at the age of 82, though the residue of his remarkable literature has long lived till this day which has now gained an unforgettable honor around the world

> “Everyone thinks of changing the world, but no one thinks of changing himself.”

>  “Respect was invented to cover the empty place where love should be.”

>  “If you look for perfection, you'll never be content.”

>   “We lost because we told ourselves we lost.”

>   “Boredom: the desire for desires.”]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ahmedsaheed2@outlook.com (Ahmed Saheed)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>